what's up everybody this is coach Brett
cont and this video is going to teach
you how to frog pump now the first thing
I want to mention about frog pumps is
that they're very polarizing two-thirds
of people love them they feel them
working their glutes so well and one of
onethird of people do not like them they
wonder what the what the craze is all
about cuz they they try them and they
don't feel them that
much so what's the deal with that well
here I have Skelly and here you can see
skelly's hip
Anatomy now I wish I had a wide variety
of human hips here to show you just to
show you the variance but what you'll
find with human hips is that you have
different shaped pelvises different hip
sockets different acetabulum different
sizes and shapes of the femur and
especially the angle at which it inserts
and so this angle and the the size and
shape of your pelvis in addition to your
glutalor you know where it attaches and
the the angle of the fibers and things
like that these are what determine the
ideal stances and widths for you during
the various glute
exercises so let's say you get down in a
frog pump and you try it and you don't
feel those glutes activating highly then
just don't do it chances are you will
prefer the wide stance glute Bridge
instead so do these
instead so now let's talk about how to
frog pump lay down get your feet
together
I walk myself in see that so my feet are
close to my butt but not too close
there's a sweet spot I also have a sweet
spot with my abduction I'm not as far as
I can abduct I'm not up here I'm kind of
in the middle somewhere Tinker around to
find The Sweet Spot with both of these
now from here I am not going to put my
head down because this might lead to
chest up hyper spinal hyperextension
instead I'm going to kind to Crunch a
little bit lift my head up and keep my
chin tucked make fists and then notice
that I'm not pushing my whole feet
together I'm only pushing my heels
together my feet are out a little bit so
just my heels are pushing together dig
your elbows in keep your ribs down
thrust
up so a couple of problems associated
with frog pumps is that number one your
net can get sore if you're tucking your
chin and number two you can slide back
and then you have to keep repositioning
your feet if you're sliding back then
your knee angle or your will open up and
then you'll start using more hamstring
so then you have to keep repositioning
so one solution to that is to elevate
your head onto something you can use a
bow ball or something else this is nice
and comfortable and now I get into a
position and I'm not using my neck
muscles to support me and then this also
prevents me from sling liting back
because this is helped keeping me in
place now let's talk set and rep schemes
well there's kind of two strategies that
I use when I do frog pumps with body
weight so sometimes I will do them and
I'll just pump out for reps and I'll
just kind of go like this and I'm not
squeezing at the top so much I'm just
pumping for reps okay when I do them
this way I go High Reps I do sets of 60
sets of 70 sets of 80 sets of 100 I can
even do sets of 120 I think one point in
time I got 180 or maybe even 200 but I
can't do that anymore um I have a lot of
my female followers with the best glutes
they're doing 500 total reps broken down
into a few sets they'll do like five
sets of 100 some of them can do 200 and
that's crazy to me but I don't think you
should get caught up so much with
Progressive overload like you shouldn't
get to where you're doing a thousand of
these um but I typically will do say you
know two to three sets of 80 to 120 uh
when I do it that way which is wrapping
out but then other days I try a
different strategy where I get into
position and then I squeeze at the top
and I'm really focusing on that big
squeeze
when I do it this way I can't get nearly
as many
reps so I'll do three three to four sets
of 25 to 50 when I do it that
way on a side note give me some props
for finally figuring out a good use for
the bosu ball now which method is better
with body weight the repping method or
the squeezing method well in theory the
repping method will be better for
generating metabolic stress you know uh
the feeling the burn
attaining a pump and the squeeze method
may be a little bit better for
generating high levels of mechanical
tension and muscle activation but really
you should do both of them so maybe you
frog pump three times a week and maybe
one day a week you do the repping method
maybe another day a week you do the
squeeze method and maybe one day a week
you do loaded frog pumps which I'll
teach you
now so now let's talk about dumbbell
frog pumps if you use a light dumbbell
like 20 30 40 50 lb and you can just set
it on top of you it's no big deal and if
you use a heavy dumbbell and you have a
trading partner they can just set it in
your lap but if you're training by
yourself you're going to want to do it
like this this is a 100 lb dumbbell I
set it down on the ground end over end
like this and then I'm just going to
roll into a a sideline position cradle
it grab a hold and roll back over like
this
okay get into
position now once I'm done I just roll
back
voila here's a cool method that requires
a preloaded barbell and a thick bar pad
now the pre-loaded barbells are ideal
compared to barbells because they have
small plates that don't interfere with
your range of motion they don't touch
the ground so all you're going to do is
Slide the thick bar pad halfway up get
into position lower this down now you're
going to have to slide it into place
okay lay
down bust out your reps and then when
you're done sit back up and then from
here and then you're
done now I'm going to teach you an open
chain frog pump the Frog pump is closed
chain a closed kinetic chain and the
Frog reverse hyper is an open kinetic
chain and they're very similar to each
other in terms of kinematics but for
some strange reason a lot of people who
don't like frog pumps that much they try
the Frog reverse hypers and they feel
them working their glutes well so even
if you don't like frog pumps you might
like these and here's how you do the
Frog reverse hyp where you just lay down
across a bench okay okay make sure you
hold on to something then get your heels
together just like you doing a frog pump
and then from here
just now a typical set and rep scheme
for these is three to four sets of 20 to
reps so now I've taught you how to frog
pump if you don't like the Frog pump
you'll know it right away you don't need
to try to fit a square peg in a into a
round hole just don't do them you might
prefer WID stance glute Bridges or maybe
even frog reverse hypers instead but if
you do like them try to find a secluded
area or a corner of the gym don't plop
down right dead center in the middle of
the gym and then be that person that
locks eye contact with all the gym
members I hope you enjoy the video bye
everybody